A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, general correspondence, RG 2, 1924-1939 FA308
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, general correspondence, RG 2, 1924-1939
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA308
74.49 Cubic Feet Standard document boxes, 1-186, 550-560 (Stack material)
Biographical/Historical note
Rockefeller Foundation general correspondence:
The existence of a separate General Correspondence file is in part a result of the reorganization in 1927-1928 of the various philanthropic boards founded by the Rockefeller Family. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial consolidated with the Foundation; some of its programs emerged in the Division of Social Sciences. The humanities interests of the General Education Board were taken over by the Foundation and provided a basis for the Foundation's new Division of Humanities. The International Health Board was reorganized and renamed the International Health Division.
Scope and Contents note
Correspondence of The Rockefeller Foundation consists principally of material not directly connected with an institutional grant. It includes: inter-office memoranda, correspondence between field officers and the home office, extracts from officers' diaries, forms and other material relating to fellowships; casual requests for information, employment, or aid; printed matter and letters of abuse received by the Foundation. As such, the General Correspondence provides insight into the day-to-day workings of the Foundation.
Programs other than public health are not amply represented in the early portion of the General Correspondence. Material on the Division of Humanities and the Division of Social Sciences is especially scanty before 1935. After 1940, the volume of this material increases steadily. Indeed, the General Correspondence files as a whole are relatively compact up to 1940; after 1941, they expand enormously.
Some of the most important features and subjects of these files are as follows:
100: STAFF COMMUNICATIONS AND INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS
This designation applies to two distinct types of documents.
(1) STAFF COMMUNICATIONS. Much of the material under this heading consists of correspondence between or regarding staff officers (eg. a field officer and a member of the home office staff), or gives details of employment and assignment of the field officer. Thus this file is in the nature of a supplement of the Foundation's personnel records. Correspondence between retirees and active staff members is often also filed under this designation, under the names of the individuals. One will also find here inter-office correspondence from the New York headquarters. Of special interest in this connection are the memos of Raymond B. Fosdick (President of the Rockefeller Foundation, 1936-1948), which usually consist of several folders for each year indicated. Some correspondence with trustees, especially Thomas B. Debevoise, may also be found here.
(2) INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS. Correspondence between The Rockefeller Foundation and the League of Nations (especially with Arthur Sweetser) lodges under this heading and persists into the 1940s. After the establishment of the United Nations Organization in 1944/5, documentation of the Foundation's cooperation with various U.N. efforts is to be found. Of special interest are the files regarding Selskar M. Gunn and Warren Weaver's service with UNRRA (1944-1946) and John Marshall's presence as an observer at the earliest organizational meetings of UNESCO (1946-1947).
200: THE UNITED STATES (201-258: Individual States and Territories)
The largest concentration of material is to be found under this designation. It is also the most miscellaneous in character. Correspondence ranges from communications with Federal agencies and departments, to letters of advice, records of interviews, appeals for aid, employment inquiries, and crank mail.
The vast bulk of these files dating between 1927 and 1939 relates to the work of the International Health Division, supplementing material previously processed as RG 5. This includes material on grants to state boards of health, training grants for public health personnel at stations in Ohio or Mississippi, and advice on administrative matters. Following the practice of the IHD, most of these earlier files were arranged under an individual state heading rather than under that of the nation as a whole. By 1935 most of the IHD activities had declined as funding became available to the states through the Federal government for this purpose. Correspondence with the individual state agencies shrank accordingly. The advisory functions of the IHD thereafter took place mainly in the form of pooling information (and occasionally personnel) with the U.S. Public Health Service.
Those states files which remain sizeable after 1935 (such as 216: Illinois-University of Chicago, and 248: Tennessee: TVA) do not relate primarily to IHD activities. In 1951, the use of state numbers in filing was almost totally abandoned.
200: UNITED STATES PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE
During World War II, the Foundation maintained close ties with USPHS, as reflected in the large file of correspondence between Foundation officers and various USPHS officials. This file refers particularly to the Foundation's effort to provide yellow fever vaccine to the Armed Forces. Also of interest for this period is a set of weekly reports on the incidence of virulent disease (plague, smallpox, etc.) around the world.
200E: FELLOWSHIPS
The earlier portion of material so designated (through 1935) is taken up with grants for training public health personnel as requested by various state boards of health. It thus amplifies the documentation of IHD activities noted above. This material includes both declinations as well as acceptances.
Similar material through the 1930s is to be found under 200S: Social Science Research Council, consisting mostly of application forms and correspondence concerning potential SSRC grantees.
For the years 1945-46, an extensive file of Postwar Fellowships follows the regular fellowship file in the General Correspondence. While the character of Foundation support of these Fellows is unclear, the advisory function of Foundation officers in their selection and placement is amply documented here.
300-833: INDIVIDUAL NATIONAL FILES
The files under this heading include administrative and budgetary material for field offices, reports of interviews with potential grantees, governmental and educational figures, diary extracts (usually travel notes, sometimes quite extensive), and miscellaneous correspondence with private and public scientific or cultural institutions and individuals. The majority of this material (especially before 1935) continues the records of the IHD in its international program (see RG 5), and deals primarily with public health programs and medical training. After 1935, the subject matter in the files becomes more diversified.
Scattered throughout these series are observations by Foundation officers on the political and social climate around the world. The Rockefeller Foundation maintained political neutrality regarding the internal affairs of host countries, and cooperated closely with governmental ministries and state-controlled universities -- especially in the areas of public health and the social sciences. Nevertheless, a close watch was kept on developments affecting intellectual freedom and the general climate of cooperation which the Foundation saw as the main prerequisite for performing or sponsoring significant work. This is reflected in the General Correspondence files, where one may find contemporary eyewitness reports and informed outside opinions on such phenomena of this century as the development of Fascism in Europe, the growth of Communism in eastern Europe and China, and the rise or fall of various dictatorships in Latin America.
Large quantities of material may be found under the following headings:
300: South America 315: Cuba 400: Great Britain 427: Canada 437: Jamaica 464: India (including 464.1: Mysore and 464.5: Travancore, through 1944) 500: France 601: China 700: Europe
The bulk of these files indicates either high levels of Foundation activity or the presence of a field office in the country concerned, and thus an "Administration" file will be found here as well as material filed alphabetically or under a program letter. Special features include the 1945-46, 500E file (France-Government Fellowships), which consist of material similar to that described under 200E for the same period. Under 700, one will also find material on the Paris Field Office supplementing that processed separately as RG 6.1.
SPECIAL TOPIC: REFUGEE SCHOLARS, 1933-1946
The General Correspondence contains a mass of material on the plight of European scholars deprived of means or work by the rise of Fascism. This material is similar and supplementary to that found in RG 1 under the same heading. Most of the material in the General Correspondence bearing on this topic may be found as listed below:
717: Germany--Refugee Scholars, 1933-1939 789: Poland-----Refugee Scholars, 1936-1939 200: U.S.---------Refugee Scholars, 1940-1945
These files generally fall into two parts:
(1) A chronological file entitled "Exiled Scholars" which consists of officer's correspondence, diary extracts, lists of exiled academics compiled from various sources, correspondence with various committees and institutions engaged in placing these scholars, and copies of the minutes of those committees with which The Rockefeller Foundation cooperated most closely.
(2) An alphabetical file of correspondence with or concerning individual scholars whose placement the Foundation sponsored or financed in part.
(3) Much material filed under 700: Europe and individual European country numbers (including 400: Great Britain, and 805: Turkey) during the period 1933-1945 also deals with this topic.
Arrangement note
The RF General Correspondence is arranged into Subgroups by Year of correspondence.
The original filing system has been retained.
Each Subgroup/Year is comprised of Series (a geographic-numeric numeric number assigned to each country, state, and/or geographic region) and Subseries (A letter designating the Program/Project area.)
General files within each series are not assinged a program letter.
Important irregularities in the original filing order are noted below:
(1) Series 100: International files are strictly alphabetical until 1941; after 1941, miscellaneous A-Z files are maintained containing small amounts of material on individuals. These immediately follow the main Series 100 International file.
(2) Correspondence with various state boards of public health precede the alphabetical file for each state or territory of the United States (201-258).
(3) Administration files for RF field offices precede the alphabetical file for the country in which they were established.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence include:
FA758 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1940-1946
FA759 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1947-1951
FA425 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1952-1957
FA400 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1958-1970
FA401 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1971-1980
FA402 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1981-1990
Related Materials
Subjects documented in the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial records, the General Education Board records and the International Health Board/Division (Rockefeller Foundation records, Record Group 5) is continued in the RF General Correspondence -- particularly in the case of the International Health Board.
Public health; Medical sciences; Medical research; Medical education; Life sciences; Jamaica; India; Humanities; Great Britain; France; Arts; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Canada; China; Charities; Communism -- Europe, Eastern; Communism; Dictatorship; Cuba; Europe; Dictatorship -- Latin America; Fascism -- Europe; Fascism; South America; United States; Refugee Scholars -- Germany; Refugees; Social sciences; Refugee Scholars -- Poland; Yellow fever -- Vaccination; Viruses -- Research; Yellow fever; Refugee Scholars -- World War II; Philanthropy; Philanthropy -- United States; Refugee Scholars -- United States
- General Correspondence, 1924
  - Japan, 1924; 1924/609
    - GRA-1 Grant, John B. "Public Health in Japan", 1924 (Box 550, Folder 3670)
- General Correspondence, 1925
  - Ceylon (Sri Lanka), 1925; 1925/462
    - Ceylon (Sri Lanka) - Malaria, 1925; 1925/462.I
      - RUS-1 Russell, Paul F. and Barnes, M. E. "A Program for the Control of Malaria in Ceylon", 1925 (Box 550, Folder 3671)
  - Algeria, 1925; 1925/501
    - Gunn, Selskar M. - "Public Health in Algeria", 1925 (Box 550, Folder 3672)
- General Correspondence, 1926
  - Brazil, 1926; 1926/305
    - Brazil - Yellow Fever, 1926; 1926/305.O
      - PUT-16 Putnam, Persis "Yellow Fever in Brazil, 1926" (Box 550, Folder 3673)
  - Ceylon (Sri Lanka), 1926; 1926/462
    - Ceylon (Sri Lanka) - Nursing, 1926; 1926/462.C
      - CAR Carter, W. S. "Data on Nursing in Ceylon", 1926 (Box 550, Folder 3674)
- General Correspondence, 1927
  - United States, 1927; 1927/200
    - Reports Concerning Flood Counties in the Rural South - FLO 1-5, 1927 (Box 550, Folder 3675)
      General note
      Stack Material
    - United States - Medical Sciences, 1927; 1927/200.A
      - LAM-1 Lambert, Robert A. "Notes on Medical Education of the Negro", 1927 (Box 550, Folder 3676)
  - Brazil, 1927; 1927/305
    - Brazil - Nursing, 1927; 1927/305.C
      - PAR-1 Parsons, Ethel S. "Modern Nursing in Brazil", 1927 (Box 550, Folder 3677)
    - Brazil - Yellow Fever, 1927; 1927/305.O
      - MUE-3 Muench, Hugo "Review of Findings in Yellow Fever Stations", 1927 (Box 550, Folder 3678)
      - ORM-1 Ormaechea, G. "Report of Yellow Fever in Parahyba do Norte, 1923-1927" (Box 550, Folder 3679)
  - Mexico, 1927; 1927/323
    - Mexico - Yellow Fever, 1927; 1927/323.O
      - RIV-1 Rivas, Pedro F. "Prophylaxis of Yellow Fever in Yucatan", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3680)
  - Panama, 1927; 1927/327
    - Panama - Hookworm, 1927; 1927/327.H
      - Shapiro, Louis SCH-3 - "Panama: General Description" SCH-4 - "Nurses - Tentative Outline", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3681)
  - Venezuela, 1927; 1927/339
    - Hill, Rolla B. HILL-1 - "Resume of Findings in Malaria and Hookworm Survey of Venezuela" HILL-5 - "Diary of Trip to Interior of Venezuela, April 9-18, 1927" (Box 551, Folder 3682)
    - Venezuela - Malaria, 1927; 1927/339.I
      - ROOT-1 Root, Francis M. "Anopheline Mosquitos of Venezuela", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3683)
    - Venezuela - Health Services, 1927; 1927/339.K
      - SAV-1 Saville, Thorndike "Report on the Water Supply of Caracas, Venezuela", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3684)
  - Ceylon (Sri Lanka), 1927; 1927/462
    - JAC-2 Jacocks, W. P. "Memo on Organization of Public Health Activities in Ceylon", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3685)
    - JAC-13 Jacocks, W. P. "Memorandum on Ceylon", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3686)
    - KEN-3 Kendrick, J. F. "Notes on Visit to Ceylon", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3687)
    - ORM-1 Ormsby-Gore, W. A. "Ceylon - Public Health", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3688)
  - India, 1927; 1927/464
    - India (Mysore), 1927; 1927/464.1
      - SWE-1 Sweet, W. C. "Notes on Conditions in Mysore State", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3689)
  - North Africa Region, 1927; 1927/485
    - North Africa Region - Hookworm, 1927; 1927/485.H
      - AUG-1 Augustine, D. L. "Brief Report on the Studies of the Hookworm Disease in Egypt...", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3690)
  - Europe, 1927; 1927/700
    - Europe - Medical Sciences, 1927; 1927/700.A
      - BAK-1 Baker, Lawrence H. "Report on European Trip", 1927 (Box 551, Folder 3691)
  - Lebanon, 1927; 1927/833
    - Lebanon - Medical Sciences, 1927; 1927/833.A
      - SY-1 Pearce, Richard M. "Medical Education in Syria, 1924-1927" (Box 551, Folder 3692)
- General Correspondence, 1928
  - International, 1928; 1928/100
    - Staff Communications and International Affairs - (D-T), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - International - Hookworm, 1928; 1928/100.H
      - Cases, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - International - Malaria, 1928; 1928/100.I
      - (B-S), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - International - Health Services, 1928; 1928/100.K
      - International Tuberculosis Union, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - International - Public Health Education, 1928; 1928/100.L
      - County Health - Balfour, M. C., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - County Health - Barnes, M. E., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - County Health - (I-M), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - International - Yellow Fever, 1928; 1928/100.O
      - Cases, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - United States, 1928; 1928/200
    - United States - (B-C), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Flood Personnel, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - United States - Medical Sciences, 1928; 1928/200.A
      - United States, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - United States - Fellowships, Scholarships, Training Awards, 1928; 1928/200.E
      - United States - (A-J), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - United States - (K-Z), 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Alabama, 1928; 1928/201
    - Alabama, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Arizona, 1928; 1928/203
    - Arizona, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Arkansas, 1928; 1928/204
    - Arkansas, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - California, 1928; 1928/205
    - California - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - California - Stanford University - Telfer, Gavin J., 1928 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Colorado, 1928; 1928/207
    - Colorado - State Board of Health - County Health Units, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Florida, 1928; 1928/211
    - Florida, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Georgia, 1928; 1928/212
    - Georgia - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Georgia - (C-S), 1928 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Georgia - (S-W), 1928 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Idaho, 1928; 1928/215
    - Idaho, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Illinois, 1928; 1928/216
    - Illinois - State Board of Health - Individuals (H), 1928 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Illinois - (M-V), 1928 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Iowa, 1928; 1928/218
    - Iowa - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Kansas, 1928; 1928/219
    - Kansas - State Board of Health (B-M), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Kentucky, 1928; 1928/220
    - Kentucky - State Board of Health - County Health, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Kentucky - (C-H), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Kentucky - (J-Y), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Louisiana, 1928; 1928/221
    - Louisiana - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Louisiana - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Louisiana - (C-K), 1928 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Maine, 1928; 1928/222
    - Maine, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Michigan, 1928; 1928/225
    - Michigan, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Mississippi, 1928; 1928/227
    - Mississippi - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Mississippi - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Mississippi - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Mississippi - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Mississippi - Reports, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Mississippi - Public Health Training - Candidates (A-S), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Mississippi - Public Health Training - Candidates (S-W), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Mississippi - (C-M), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Mississippi - Public Health, 1928/227.J
      - Mississippi Public Health Demonstrations, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Missouri, 1928; 1928/228
    - Missouri - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Missouri - (C-S), 1928 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Montana, 1928; 1928/229
    - Montana - State Board of Health - Jones, Dr. D. R., 1928 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Nebraska, 1928; 1928/230
    - Nebraska, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Nevada, 1928; 1928/231
    - Nevada, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - New Hampshire, 1928; 1928/232
    - New Hampshire, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - New Jersey, 1928; 1928/233
    - New Jersey, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - New Mexico, 1928; 1928/234
    - New Mexico - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - North Carolina, 1928; 1928/236
    - North Carolina - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - North Carolina - Natural Sciences and Agriculture, 1928; 1928/236.D
      - Chase, H. W., 1928 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - North Dakota, 1928; 1928/237
    - North Dakota, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Ohio, 1928; 1928/238
    - Ohio - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Ohio - (B-W), 1928 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Ohio - Greenville Training Center - Reports, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Oklahoma, 1928; 1928/239
    - Oklahoma - State Board of Health - Ricks, Dr. H. C., 1928 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Oregon, 1928; 1928/240
    - Oregon, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Pennsylvania, 1928; 1928/241
    - Pennsylvania, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Rhode Island, 1928; 1928/244
    - Rhode Island, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - South Carolina, 1928; 1928/246
    - South Carolina, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - South Carolina, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - South Carolina - (B-W), 1928 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - South Dakota, 1928; 1928/247
    - South Dakota, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Tennessee, 1928; 1928/248
    - Tennessee - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Tennessee - State Board of Health, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Tennessee - State Board of Health - Cooke, Mary P., 1928 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Utah, 1928; 1928/250
    - Utah, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Vermont, 1928; 1928/251
    - Vermont, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Virginia, 1928; 1928/252
    - Virginia, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Washington, 1928; 1928/253
    - Washington, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - West Virginia, 1928; 1928/254
    - West Virginia, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - West Virginia, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Wyoming, 1928; 1928/256
    - Wyoming, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Argentina, 1928; 02.1928/301
    - Argentina - Malaria, 1928; 1928/301.I
      - Argentina - Cabral - Lopez, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 60)
      - Argentina - Rickard, E. R., 1928 (Box 8, Folder 60)
      - Argentina - Soper, Fred L., 1928 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Brazil, 1928; 1928/305
    - Brazil - Yellow Fever, 1928; 1928/305.O
      - Brazil, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 62)
      - BIAO-1 Biao, Maria "Diary re investigation of Estancia, Usina Castello, and Patrocino de Corte", 1928 (Box 552, Folder 3693)
      - PUT-15 Putnam, Persis "Indices of Yellow Fever Infectibility for the City of Bahia, Brazil", 1928 (Box 552, Folder 3694)
      - SMI-1 Smith, Lucins C. "Report of Inspectors made in Certain Interior Towns", 1928 (Box 552, Folder 3695)
      - SMI-2 Smith, Lucins C. Report on Yellow Fever in Ceara, 1928 (Box 552, Folder 3696)
  - Colombia, 1928; 1928/311
    - Colombia - Nursing, 1928; 1928/311.C
      - Colombia, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Colombia - Hookworm, 1928; 1928/311.H
      - Colombia, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Colombia - Malaria, 1928; 1928/311.I
      - Colombia, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Costa Rica, 1928; 1928/313
    - Costa Rica - Hookworm, 1928; 1928/313.H
    - Costa Rica - Health Services, 1928; 1928/313.K
      - Costa Rica, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 65)
  - Guatemala, 1928; 1928/319
    - Guatemala - Hookworm, 1928; 1928/319.H
      - Elmendorf, John E., 1928 (Box 8, Folder 66)
      - Guatemala, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Guatemala - Health Services, 1928; 1928/319.K
      - Guatemala - Elmendorf, John E., 1928 (Box 8, Folder 67)
  - Mexico, 1928; 1928/323
    - Mexico - Carr, Henry P., 1928 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Nicaragua, 1928; 1928/325